chapter five of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is in the public
domain Black Beauty by Anna suul chapter 5 A Fair Start The name of the coachman was John
Manley he had a wife and one little child, and they lived in the coachman's
cottage, very near the stables. The next morning he took me into
the yard and gave me a good grooming, and
just as I was going into my box, with my coat soft and bright, the squire came in
to look at me, and seemed pleased. “John,” he said, “I meant to have tried the new horse
this morning, but I have other business.
You may as well take him around after breakfast; go by the common and the
Highwood, and back by the watermill and the river; that will show his paces.” “I
will, sir,” said John. After breakfast he came and fitted me with a bridle. He was
very particular in letting out and taking scking in the straps, to fit my
head comfortably; then he bought a saddle, but it was not broad enough for my back;
he saw it in a minute and went for another, which fitted nicely. He rode me
first slowly, then a trot, then a caner and when we were on the common he gave
me a light touch with his whip, and we had a splendid
gallop. “Ho, ho! my boy,” he said, as he pulled me up, “you would like to follow the
hounds, I think.” As we came back through the park we met the squad fire and Mrs. Gordon
walking; they stopped, and JN jumped off.
“Well JN how does he go First Rate sir,”
answered JN he is as fleet as a deer, and has a fine spirit too; but the lightest
touch of the rain will guide him. Down at the end of the common we met one of
those traveling carts hung all over with baskets, rugs, and such like; you know, sir,
many horses will not pass those carts quietly; he just took a good look at it,
and then went on as quiet and pleasant as could be. They were shooting rabbits
near the I would and a gun went off close by; he pulled up a little and
looked, but did not stir a step to right or left. I just held the rain steady and
did not hurry him, and it's my opinion he has not been frightened or ill-used while he was
young.” “That's well,” said the squire, “I will try him myself
tomorrow The next day I was brought up for my master. I remembered my mother's
counsel and my good old Masters and I tried to do exactly what he wanted me to
do. I found he was a very good rider, and thoughtful for his horse
too. When he came home the lady was at
the hall door as he rode up. “Well, my dear,”
she said, “how do you like him?” “He is exactly what John said,” he replied; “a
pleasant creature I never wish to mount.
What should we call him?” “Would you like Ebony?” said she; “he is as black as
ebony.” “No, not Ebony.” “Will you call him Blackbird, like your uncle's old
horse?” “No, he is far handsomer than old Blackbird ever
was.” “Yes,” she said, “he really is quite a beauty, and he has such a sweet,
good-tempered face, and such a fine, intelligent eye— —what do you say to calling him Black
Beauty?” “Black Beauty— —why, yes, I think that is a very good name. If you like it
she'll be his name;” and so it was.
When John went into the stable he told James that master and mistress had
chosen a good, sensible English name for me, that meant something; not like Morango
or Pegasus, or abdala They both laughed, and James said,
“If it was not for bringing back the past, I should have named him robroy for I
never saw two horses more alike.” “That's no wonder,” said John; “didn't
you know that Farmer Gray's old Duchess was the mother of them both?”
I had never heard that before; and so poor robroy who was killed at that hunt was my
brother! I did not wonder that my mother was so troubled. It seems that horses
have no relations; at least they never know each other after they are
sold. John seemed very proud of me; he used to make my man and tail almost as
smooth as a lady's hair, and he would talk to me a great deal; of course I did
not understand all he said, but I learned more and more to know what he meant, and
what he wanted me to do. I grew very fond
of him, he was so gentle and kind; he seemed to know just how a horse feels,
and when he cleaned me he knew the tender places and the ticklish places;
when he brushed my head he went as carefully over my eyes as if they were
his own, and never stirred up any ill temper James Howard, the stable boy, was
just as gentle and pleasant in his way, so I thought myself well off.
There was another man who helped in the yard, but he had very little to do with
Ginger and me. A few days after this I had to go out
with Ginger in the carriage. I wondered how we should get on together; but except
laying her ears back when I was led up to her, she behaved very well. She did her
work honestly, and did her full share, and I never wish to have a better partner in double
harness. When we came to a hill, instead of slackening her pace, she would throw
her weight right right into the collar, and pull away straight up. We had both
the same sort of courage at our work, and JN had oftener to hold us in than to
urge us forward; he never had to use the whip with either of us; then our paces
were much the same, and I found it very easy to keep step with her when trotting,
which made it pleasant, and master always liked it when we kept step well, and so did
JN After we had been out two or three times together we grew quite friendly
and sociable, which made me feel very much at home. As for Mary legs he and I soon
became great friends; he was such a cheerful, plucky, good-tempered little
fellow that he was a favorite with everyone and especially with Miss Jesse
and Flora, who used to ride him about in the orchard, and have fine games with him
and their little dog Frisky. Our master had two other horses
that stood in another stable. One was Justice, a ran cob, used for riding or for
the luggage cart; the other was an old brown hunter, named Sir Oliver; he was
past work now, but was a great favorite with the master, who gave him the run of
the park; he sometimes did a little light carting on the estate, or carried one of
the young ladies when they rode out with their father, for he was very gentle and
could be trusted with a child as well as merry legs The cob was a strong,
well-made, good-tempered horse, and we sometimes had a little chat in the
paddock, but of course I could not be so intimate with him as with Ginger, who
stood in the same stable end of chapter